Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 11. Print matter (1881-2017; 79.25 linear feet), 217002; 79.25 Linear feet
  - Series II. Student publications, 1901-2015; 217004; 28 Linear feet
    - The Kaleidoscope, 1991-2002; 217207 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 9)
    - Dope Ink Prints (4 folders), 1995-2013; 217209 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 10-13)
    - Community Server, 1996-2001; 217211 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 14)
    - Middle School publications (4 folders), 1930, 1954-2015 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 15-18)
      Newspapers and literary publications from Middle School students, or Form I and II students.
    - Art and photography magazines (3 folders), 1935-2010 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 19-21)
    - Fieldston Press guides, 1935, 1974, undated (Offsite-box 168, Folder 22)
    - Occasional student publications (6 folders), 1934, 1990-2008 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 1-6)
      The Eagle Chinese (undated), The Fieldston Historical Review (1999-2000, 2007-2008), The Fieldston Review (1995), The Gouda (2006), The Student Looks At War (1935), S.U.M.E Chronicle (1990).
    - Other occasional publications (5 folders), 1931-2014 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 7-11)
      Includes commencement booklet produced by the Teacher Education Department class of 1936.
    - Fieldston News, 1928-1968 (Offsite-box 331)
      Incomplete run, especially before 1960.
    - Fieldston News, 1969-1980 (Offsite-box 332)
    - Fieldston News, 1981-1999 (Offsite-box 333)
    - Fieldston News, 2000-2009 (Offsite-box 334)
    - Fieldston News - special publications (2 folders), 1929-2010 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 12-13)
    - Hilltop Press and Interschool News, 1949, 1972-1984 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 14)
    - The Fieldston Chronicle (2 folders), 1991-1999 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 15-16)
    - Fieldston guides (2 folders), 1960-1980, 2013 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 17-18)
      Guides to campus and extracurricular activities written by students. Some published by the Student Council or Fieldston News.
    - Midtown and Fieldston Lower occasional publications (4 folders), 1930-1999 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 19-22)
    - Midtown and Fieldston Lower occasional publications - cookbooks, undated (Offsite-box 193, Folder 6)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1929-1934 (Offsite-box 178)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1935-1943 (Offsite-box 179)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1944-1954 (Offsite-box 180)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1955-1963 (Offsite-box 181)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1964-1971 (Offsite-box 182)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1972-1979 (Offsite-box 183)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1980-1986 (Offsite-box 184)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1987-1993 (Offsite-box 185)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 1994-1999 (Offsite-box 186)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 2000-2005 (Offsite-box 187)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 2006-2009, 2011 (Offsite-box 188)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 2012, 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 189)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston - with inscriptions, 1940-2000 (Offsite-box 192)
      Yearbooks from various years, with personal inscriptions by students.
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston Middle, 2011, 2013-2015 (Offsite-box 189)
    - Yearbooks, Midtown and Fieldston Lower (6 folders), 1992-2011 (Offsite-box 193, Folder 7-12)
    - Compiled publications - Fieldston News and ECS Reporter (13 folders), 1932-1963 (Offsite-box 190, Folder 1-13)
      Compiled copies of Fieldston News, 1940-1970, and the ECS Reporter, 1952-1981. Also includes one issue of the Hilltop Press, and several copies of the Intelligencer. "From E.L. 8 April 1953" Some from the office of faculty Elbert Lenrow.
    - Compiled publications - Fieldston News and ECS Reporter, 1952-1981 (Offsite-box 191)
    - Yearbooks, Fieldston, 2016 (Offsite-box 340)
  - Series III. Parents' and Teachers' Association, 1918-2001; 217006; 3.5 Linear feet
    Materials in this series were created by the Parent and Teacher Association, sometimes in partnership with the administration.
    This series begins with journals and newsletters, followed by ephemera and administrative materials.
    - School and Home, 1918-1937; 217225 (Offsite-box 339)
    - School and Home (2 folders), 1938-1941; 217226 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 23-24)
    - School and Home - reprints and indices, 1925-1926, undated; 217227 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 25)
    - The Bulletin, 1928-1939; 217228 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 1)
    - Midtown Bulletin (2 folders), 1965-1975, 1990-1994; 217229 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 2-3)
    - Midtown Matters, 217230 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 4)
    - Ethical Culture P&T Bulletin (3 folders), 1994-2001; 217231 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 5-7)
    - Fieldston Lower School P&T News and Bulletin (4 folders), 1947-1995; 217232 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 8-11)
    - Fieldston P&T News (2 folders), 1990-2001; 217233 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 12-13)
    - Administrative materials, 1981-1996, undated; 217234 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 14)
      Includes copy of Leadership Guidelines and P&T Association constitution and by-laws (undated).
    - Ephemera, 1948-1996, undated; 217235 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous and occasional publications (3 folders), 1948-1991, undated; 217236 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 16-18)
    - Fieldston Lower School P&T News and Bulletin - bound copies, 1958-1973 (Offsite-box 329)
    - School and Home - bound copies, 1918-1937 (Offsite-box 335)
  - Series IV. Alumni publications, 1911-2010; 217005; 2 Linear feet
    This series contains materials created by alumni, the Alumni Association, or the administration for use by alumni.
    Items in the series are arranged largely in chronological order.
    - Alumni publications (3 folders), 1911-1940; 217216 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 1-3)
      The Alumni Magazine, the Alumni Bulletin, the Ethical-Fieldston Alumni News, and the Ethical Culture School Record.
    - Alumni Annual (3 folders), 1942-1949, 1953; 217217 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 4-6)
    - Ephemera, 1953-2010; 217218 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 7)
      Ephemera created by the school or the Alumni Association for events or fundraisers.
    - Alumni directories (5 folders), 1978-2005; 217219 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 8-12)
    - Reunion books and questionnaires (8 folders), 1937-1983; 217220 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 13-20)
      Books published at various intervals for Fieldston classes of 1920-1979.
    - Reunion books and questionnaires (12 folders), 1960-2000; 217221 (Offsite-box 177, Folder 1-12)
    - Alumni/faculty publications list, 1958-1962; 217222 (Offsite-box 177, Folder 13)
    - Studies of alumni, 1959, 1978; 217223 (Offsite-box 177, Folder 14)
      Reports and brochures.
  - Series V. (RESTRICTED) Duplicate print matter and ephemera, 217007; 27.5 Linear feet
    Boxes in this series only contain excess copies of print matter and ephemera found elsewhere in this record group. Because the material is redundant it is not available for regular Reading Read use but is reserved for exhibition or other special uses only for exhibition purposes.
    - Duplicates, Series I: School brochures and ephemera, 1900s-1940s. (Offsite-box 136)
    - Duplicates, Series I: School brochures and ephemera, 1950s-1970s. Parent and teacher handbooks. (Offsite-box 137)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Teaching and Learning. Ethical Culture School Record. (Offsite-box 138)
    - Duplicates, Series I: calendars, annual reports, Centennial Conference reports, publications by faculty. (Offsite-box 139)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Ephemera and newsletters, mostly after 1990. (Offsite-box 140)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Course of study catalogs. (Offsite-box 141)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Course of study catalogs. Fieldston evaluations (1970s). "The First Sixty Years" by Mabel Goodlander. Admissions publications. (Offsite-box 142)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Directories (student and faculty). (Offsite-box 143)
    - Duplicates, Series I: Development ephemera. Ephemera from other institutions. (Offsite-box 144)
    - Duplicates, Series I: ECS Reporter. (Offsite-box 154)
    - Duplicates, Series I: ECS Reporter, 1956-1983 (Offsite-box 336)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Yearbooks, 1929-1935, 1937-1955. (Offsite-box 145)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Yearbooks, 1955-1975. (Offsite-box 146)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Yearbooks, 1976-1992. (Offsite-box 148)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Yearbooks, 1993-2004. (Offsite-box 147)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Yearbooks, 2005-2009, 2011-2012, 2015. (Offsite-box 156)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Literary magazines. (Offsite-box 171)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Inklings (1918-1932), New Inklings (1938-1946), early elementary yearbooks (1900s-1920s). (Offsite-box 172)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Inklings (1901-1917). (Offsite-box 173)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Fieldston News, with some other student publications. (Offsite-box 149)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Fieldston student publications. (Offsite-box 150)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Fieldston student publications: New Inklings 1947-1990s. Speak Out. (Offsite-box 151)
    - Duplicates, Series II: Fieldston student publications. (Offsite-box 152)
    - Duplicates, Series III: Alumni printed matter. (Offsite-box 153)
    - Duplicates, Series IV: School and Home. (Offsite-box 155)
    - Duplicates, Various: mostly Parent and Teacher Association. (Offsite-box 169)
    - Duplicates, Various: ECS Reporter, School and Home News, School and Home. (Offsite-box 170)
  - Series VI. Published books, 1895-1994; 3 Linear feet
    This series contains published works. Several books were written by faculty and administrators, or mention the Ethical Culture Schools, while others were possibly used in teaching or as personal staff copies.
    This series in arranged in chronological order.
    - Kindergarten Magazine and Review, 1895-1902 (Offsite-box 313)
      Kindergarden Magazine, Vol VIII, 1895-1896. Kindergarden Review, Volume VIII, 1897. Kindergarden Magazine, Vol XIV, 1901-1902.
    - Written by faculty and administrators, 1902-1956 (Offsite-box 312)
      The Moral Instruction of Children, by Felix Adler, 1902. Training Children to Study, by Bessie W. Stillman, 1928. The Passing of the Recitation, by V.T. Thayer, 1928. Reorganizing Secondary Education, by V.T. Thayer, Caroline B. Zachry, and Ruth Kotinsky, 1939. Creative Drama in the Lower School, by Corinne Brown, 1929. American Education Under Fire, by V.T. Thayer, 1944. Remedial Training for Children with Specific Disability in Reading, Spelling, and Penmanship: Part Two Remedial Procedures, by Anna Gillingham and Bessie W. Stillman, 1946. A Spelling Curriculum, by Sally B. Childs, 1955. Remedial Training for Children with Specific Disability in Reading, Spelling, and Penmanship, by by Anna Gillingham and Bessie W. Stillman, 1956.
    - Published by the Ethical Culture School, 1912-1915, circa 1940 (Offsite-box 312)
      Festivals and Plays in Schools and Elsewhere, by Percival Chubb, 1912. America the Wonderland: A Patriotic Festival, 1915. Three copies (from orginal run of 200) of Plato's Crito, printed by Graphic Arts Department students at the Fieldston School Press, undated (with donor note, 1940).
    - Other books, 1917-1985 (Offsite-box 314)
      Friedrich Froebel's Pedagogics of the Kindergarten, translated by Josephine Jarvis, 1917. Living in a World of Science: Book Two, by Morris Meister, 1935. Inside Asia, by John Gunther, 1939. An Essay on Morals, by Philip Wylie, 1947. Education and Morals: An Experimentalist Philosophy of Education, by John L. Childs, 1950 (signed copy). Everyday Junior Mathematics, by William Betz, 1951. Toward an Understanding of the U.S.S.R., by Michael T. Florinsky, 1953. The Last Angry Man, by Gerald Green, 1956. The Ark of Noah: A Collection of Sermons, by Rabbi Noah Kaplan, 1957 (in Hebrew). Russia: A History and Interpretation Volume II, by Michael T. Florinsky, 1958. The Small Mosaics of Mr. and Mrs. Engel, by Patricia Collinge, 1959. Archaeology in the Holy Land, by Kathleen M. Kenyon, 1960. The Lifetime Reading Plan, by Clifton Fadiman, 1960. How to Get More for Your Money, by Sylvia Porter, 1961 (signed copy). Collected Poems, Basil Bunting, 1985
    - Written by Chairs of the Board of Governors, 1947-1994 (Offsite-box 312)
      Human Relations: A Challenge to Our Public Schools, by Frank E. Karelsen, Jr., 1947. The Existential Pleasures of Engineering, by Samuel C. Florman, 1994.
    - Biographies, 1959-1981 (Offsite-box 313)
      A Ministry to Man: The Life of John Lovejoy Elliott, by Tay Hohoff, 1959. Felix Adler and Ethical Culture: Memories and Studies, by Horace L. Friess, 1981.
    - Ethical Culture Society, 1969-1990 (Offsite-box 313)
      Toward Common Ground: The Story of The Ethical Societies in the United States, by Howard Radest, 1969. The Woman of the Wood: A Tale from Old Russia, as told by Algernon D. Black, 1973. A Lively Connection: Intimate Encounters with the Ethical Movement in America, 1978. Can We Teach Ethics, by Howard B. Radest, 1989. With inscription to "Janet." The Devil and Secular Humanism: The Children of the Enlightenment, by Howard B. Radest, 1990. With inscription to "Janet."
    - Directories, 1989-1993 (Offsite-box 313)
      The Manhattan Directory of Private Nursery Schools, by Linda Faulhaber, 1989. New York Independent Schools Directory, published by Parents League of New York, 1991-1993.
- Record Group 12. History of the Ethical Culture Schools (1902-2015; 4 linear feet), 216996; 4 Linear feet
  This record group contains materials related to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School's efforts to record and preserve their institutional history. This includes the collection of historical materials and the creation of written narratives and oral histories, as well as the management of the school's institutional archives.
  This record group is arranged in two series:
  Series I. Narratives and records
  Series II. Archives management
  - Series I. Narratives and records, 1902-2015; 216906; 3 Linear feet
    Materials in this series relate to efforts to record the history of the Ethical Culture Fieldston Schools. Types of materials include written accounts of the school's history, newspaper clippings, and transcripts of oral history interviews with students and faculty.
    This series follows the previous arrangement of materials.
    - Chronologies, undated; 217051 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 1)
      Also contains copies of early meeting minutes and other documents.
    - Assembled historical materials (3 folders), 1942-1997, undated; 217052 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 2-9)
      Ephemera, timelines, short histories, excerpts from school publications, alumni and faculty reminiscences, and other materials relating to the history of the Ethical Culture Fieldston School.
    - Assembled historical materials (4 folders), 1942-2005 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 12-15)
      Many facsimiles, with some original materials, collected on the history of the school. Includes folder on the Black and Latino Students Club, several mid-twentieth century photographs of athletics activities and staff, postcard from Maxine Kingston, and letter from Wendy Wasserstein.
    - News clippings (6 folders), 1902-2015 (Offsite-box 195, Folder 10-16)
    - Written histories (4 folders), 1980-1985, 1999, undated (Offsite-box 195, Folder 17-20)
      Includes "Ethical Culture: The First Hundred Years," a radio script by alumni Ernest Kinoy and Daniel Powers Kinoy; draft text and materials for "The Place Where We Met" by Kathe Jervis; and "Dramatic Activities at the Ethical Culture School, 1878-1930," dissertation text by Virginia Page Tennyson.
    - Oral history transcripts, 1964 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 1)
      Transcripts of interviews with faculty, students, and members of the Board of Trustees.
    - Oral history transcripts - Elbert Lenrow (4 folders), 1989 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 2-9)
      Drafts, revisions, and final copies of transcripts of oral history interview with faculty member Elbert Lenrow. Includes floppy disk.
    - Oral history transcripts - senior students (4 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 196, Folder 10-13)
    - Oral history transcripts - senior students (4 folders), 1999 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 1-4)
  - Series II. Archives management, 1971-2008; 1 Linear feet
    This series contains materials related to internal efforts to arrange, describe, and preserve the Ethical Culture Fieldston School's institutional archives. Types of materials include correspondence, meeting records, planning materials, inventories, and finding aids.
    Additional materials related to the archival efforts of Director of Alumni Relations Toby Himmel can be found in Record Group 8, Alumni and alumni relations.
    - Archives management (6 folders), 1983-2001 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 5-10)
    - Archives arrangement and storage (7 folders), 1985-2002 (Offsite-box 197, Folder 11-17)
      Inventory of records (final copy with notes and drafts) box lists, finding aids.
    - Archives arrangement and storage (6 folders), 1987-2008 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 1-6)
      Finding aids, inventories, plan for future archives projects.
    - Reference requests (5 folders), 1971-2002 (Offsite-box 198, Folder 7-11)
    - Archive subject index, undated (Offsite-box 316)
      Box of index cards, with subjects in alphabetical order, and correspondening location of archival materials. Also includes lists of school and student periodicals.
- Record Group 13. Ethics Department and the Society for Ethical Culture (1901-1999; 7.5 linear feet), 7.5 Linear feet
  This record group contains materials related to the Society for Ethical Culture, its shared philosophies with the Ethical Culture Fieldston School, and ethics program curriculum. The Society for Ethical Culture was established in 1876 by Felix Adler, who founded the Workingman's School two years later. In 1895, the Society took governance of the newly named Ethical Culture School. Since 1996, the Society and School have been officially separate organizations.
  Based on the Society's teaching, the ethics program was intended to guide students both in their personal lives and their places in the greater world. It was described in 1984 as "based on the personal, social, and intellectual development of our students and responding to the moral issues that they meet in experiences."
  Types of materials include correspondence, reports, ephemera (produced both by the Society and ECFS), legal documents, meeting minutes, teacher guides, and curriculum materials. Records were created throughout the 20th century, but the bulk of materials are dated between the 1970s and 1990s.
  Series I. The Society for Ethical Culture
  Series II. Ethics Department
  - Series I. Society for Ethical Culture, 1901-1999; 2.5 Linear feet
    Records in this series involve the relationship between the Society for Ethical Culture and the Ethical Culture Fieldston School. Subjects include the influence of Society teachings on the School's philosophy, the use of shared spaces in the Central Park West building, the administration of shared funds, and the formal financial separation of the two organizations in the 1990s.
    It also includes papers of Algernon Black, an ECFS alumni and long-time leader of the Society, as well as early 1990s records related to the separation, from the office of Head of School Jeanne Amster.
    This series is arranged in chronological order, following earlier processing efforts.
    - Ephemera, 1901-1999 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 1)
      Includes event programs and newsletters.
    - Ephemera (4 folders), 1922-1960 (Offsite-box 131, Folder 10-13)
      Primarily pamphlets on issues and texts of addresses.
    - Algernon Black papers (9 folders), 1931-1983 (Offsite-box 127, Folder 1-9)
      Materials from longtime leader of the Ethical Culture Society, and at one time head of Ethics Department at the Ethical Culture Schools. Items relate to moral education and the Ethical Culture Schools, with types of items including correspondence, essays, memorandum, notes, ephemera, news clippings, and transcripts of addresses and discussions with students. Files also include Ethical Culture Society committee meeting minutes and correspondence with Luther Tate.
    - "The Student Looks at War" handbook (2 folders), 1935-1936 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 2)
      Press release from the Society on the release of the book by the Fieldston Junior Peace Council, with correspondence (mainly requests for copies.)
    - Addresses (4 folders), 1936-1946 (Offsite-box 131, Offsite-box 14-17)
      Texts of talks given at Society meetings, most between 1945-1946.
    - School-Society relationship - correspondence and memoranda (4 folders), 1942-1996 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 3-6)
      Includes 1940s correspondence between Society leaders and Herbert A. Wolf (chairman of the Ethical Culture School Board of Governors), 1970s and 1980s records of the Council on Educational Philosophy and the School-Society Relations Committee, and 1980s correspondence on the use of shared space and the visit of President of Nicaragua Daniel Ortega to the Society in 1985.
    - School philosophy (2 folders), 1952-1989 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 7-8)
      Mission statements and discussions of objectives, as well as records of the Council on Education Philosophy, 1976-1979.
    - Sutro estate - legal materials (2 folders), 1972-1984 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 9-10)
      Files of correspondence and documents, sent from the law offices of M. S. and I. S. Isaacs. Original folder titles: Re: Sutro correspondence, Re: Sutro - Will and Financial data, Re: classification of Society Funds.
    - Discussion of separation (2 folders), 1976-1985 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 11-12)
      Includes proposed changes to by-laws, 1985.
    - School-Society relationship (2 folders), 1980-1990 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 13-14)
      Correspondence and other documents from the administration and Board of Governors.
    - Jeanne Amster papers - Society relationship (4 folders), 1992-1994 (Offsite-box 125, Folder 15-18)
      Correspondence, Board of Governors materials, meeting minutes, and memoranda regarding School-Society relationships and separation terms, from the office of Head of School Jeanne Amster. In original reverse chronological order.
    - Jeanne Amster papers - Society relationship (4 folders), 1992-1993 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 1-4)
    - Financial matters (2 folders), 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 5-6)
    - Separation (4 folders), 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 7-10)
      Correspondence, legal documents, memorandum, and copy of 1995 provisional charter.
    - Closing documents and exhibits (4 folders), 1996 (Offsite-box 126, Folder 11-13)
      Three bound sets of legal and financial documents.
    - School and Society matters, 1966-1983 (Offsite-box 295, Folder 17)
      Includes correspondence of Algernon Black and Victoria Wagner.
  - Series II. Ethics program, 1901-1993; 5 Linear feet
    This series contains records of the Ethics program at all grade levels of the Ethical Culture Fieldston Schools. The Ethics curriculum is built on humanistic teachings, with subjects including interpersonal relationships, mental and physical health, current events, history, religion, and moral theory. There is a focus on teaching through examples in myths, folklore, and fiction throughout the program.
    As Educational Director Dr. V.T. Thayer wrote of the program's goals in 1936, "One, that children be led through the school to discover and to develop their unique possibilities of mind and character; and second that their growth should proceed at all times in sensitive response to fundamental aspects of the society in which they live and move and have their being."